Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adopted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
In the year 1722,
Emperor Kangxi of the Qing Dynasty passed away.
General Nian Gengyao and General Longkodo
played a crucial role in Emperor Yongzheng's accession to the throne.
Emperor Yongzheng, 45, was the Fourth Prince named Yin Zhen.
He held the two generals in high esteem,
which won them unrivaled political powers.
All kneel!
All bow!
Second time!
Third time!
All rise!
By the Grace of Heaven, His Majesty
awards Longkodo the First-Order Honor
for his loyal service to the prior Emperor and His Majesty.
(Longkodo)
By the Grace of Heaven, His Majesty
awards Longkodo the First-Order Honor
for his loyal service to the prior Emperor and His Majesty.
Zhang Tingyu [he's not happy]
Longkodo is appointed as Minister of Personnel,
and Director of Ethnic and Territorial Affairs.
His Majesty awards Nian Gengyao the Second-Order Honor.
(Nian Gengyao)
He will be in charge of military affairs
(Zhen Yuandao)
(Gūwalgiya Emin)
and the appointment of frontier officials.
This is His Majesty's edict.
I thank His Majesty.
(whispering) His Majesty does think highly of General Nian.
Congratulations, General Long!
We are grateful for your exceptional contribution to our country.
Congratulations, General Nian!
His Majesty truly appreciates your service.
Sir, you certainly are His Majesty's right-hand man.
General Nian!
Greetings, General Nian!
How can I help you, Mr. Su?
His Majesty is concerned with your arm injury.
He instructed me to send you the
specially-made ointment for the wound.
I HUMBLY thank His Majesty for the heavenly grace.
May I ask how my sister is doing in the palace?
No one is comparable with your sister, Consort Fleur.
There's nothing to worry about her.
(sneer) Thanks for taking care of her.
My pleasure.
(sounding the night watches)
Hall of Mental Cultivation
[the Emperor's residence]
Your Majesty, an official from Attendance Services is here.
Your Majesty, please select one.
(Xu Jinliang)
Your Majesty has not been visiting
any consorts for the past two weeks.
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager
is going to blame my negligence.
Your Majesty, Please!
She'll just blame you for talking too much.
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager is here.
Show her in quickly.
Empress Dowager Uya Chengbi
Peace to Your Majesty.
Imperial Mother.
The Imperial Kitchen made me sweet mung bean soup with lily roots.
It calms me down on such a hot night.
I brought you some, figuring you must be awake.
Thank you, Imperial Mother.
General Long got the pickles for Her Majesty from the south.
He said it is more refreshing than what we have here in Beijing.
Here we go.
Don't be upset. We'll get used to it.
It's been over 6 months since His Majesty's coronation.
But you can count on one hand the times he slept in the harem.
(sigh) I understand your frustration of displeasing
both His Majesty and Her Majesty.
(gasp) Thank you for your understanding, Mr Su.
I would be most grateful if
you could often remind His Majesty
that the concubines miss him like the deserts miss the rain
I would like to oblige, but His Majesty has been so busy
lately that he could only sleep for 4-6 hours.
I had no chance to mention the concubines.
Imperial Mother, if you are bothered by the heat,
I will have ice sent to your palace .
My aging body is not as sensitive to the heat.
You should care more about your health.
Work cannot be finished in one day.
I understand.
Did you take some time to look into
the Third Prince's schoolwork?
I did. He was coming along with his calligraphy,
but not so much with the books.
(sigh) The prior Emperor had 24 princes.
You can't compare to him.
I am not as blessed as Father. I only have three sons.
It's not your fault. He had more children because he had more concubines.
Your harem is almost empty.
The Empress, Consort Honnête,
and Consort Astuce, they are not getting any younger.
I understand.
It is the Imperial Family's priority to have children in plenty,
so that we can pass the throne through generations.
That is why we have a Concubine Selection every three years.
Of course.
So, we will have a Selection.
Yes, I accept your arrangement.
(chuckle) I am too old to arrange for you.
The Imperial Household Department
will set the dates for a few rounds of selection.
I will just happily wait for more grandchildren.
I will let Consort Fleur take charge of the Selection,
not to put more burden on the Empress.
Consort Fleur is more than just a pretty face.
She has been exclusively in favor for these years.
Now it's better for you have someone to balance with her.
Sure.
But there's something I'd like to change.
What is it?
One Selection is enough for me.
It is too costly to do it every three years.
I see Han people [the dominant ethnic group] as family to us Manchus.
I'd like more concubines from the Han Banners.
[Banner is a military establishment in 8 ranks]
(chuckle) I'm fine with that.
I'm glad you are having new concubines.
But do not make the old ones feel neglected.
You should often visit them no matter how much work you have.
Especially the Empress, she is "the center of the harem".
I'll remember that.
Palace of Great Benevolence [the Empress’ palace]
Thanks for coming at this time.
I hope I did not interrupt your afternoon nap.
Your Majesty does always have the time to nap.
(The Empress)
I am not as fortunate.
I was just wondering if everything is ready
for the final round of the Selection.
(Consort Flear, Nian Shilan)
Don't worry, Your Majesty.
Huang Guiquan had everything ready by noon.
His Majesty is on a tight budget to select concubines.
But I must not make him lose face.
Who could understand the difficulty of my job?
(sigh) I must thank you for your hard work.
I hope you will like the new pastries I ordered for you.
Spring.
[Another maid of the Empress]
Please help yourself.
(slight sigh) Or would you like a recommendation?
Autumn, bring forward the peony rolls.
Song Zhi.
[Consort Hua's lead maid]
I thank Your Majesty.
I beg Your Majesty's pardon!
I didn't mean to.
What is wrong with you?
It is not your first day in the Palace.
You must ask for Her Majesty's punishment.
I do beg Your Majesty's pardon.
I did expect more from you as my dowry maid.
If Her Majesty does not forgive you, I shall not let you off easy.
It's all right, Shilan.
Nothing to be angry about.
I thank Your Majesty for your magnanimity to my clumsy maid.
She will be better trained next time.
A dowry maid is different from the other servants.
Song Zhi must be inexperienced with menial jobs.
There is no need to be mad at her, is there?
Fuzi.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Peace to Your Highness.
Fuzi was recently sent to my palace by the Household Department.
She's a competent maid. I'll let you have her.
Song Zhi is good enough, and my palace is well staffed.
Your Majesty should keep Fuzi.
Your palace is staffed with the best servants.
I hope Fuzi will have the chance to learn from them.
She can also do menial jobs for Song Zhi.
I have to go now.
Move!
Yes.
I hope everything is fine with the Selection.
His Majesty does need new concubines for the family.
Stay away!
Do you not know your place?
Stay out of Her Highness's sight!
Dear Buddha, although I am unable to choose my own husband,
I wish to marry the best man in this world.
I hope we will grow old and gray together.
Dear Buddha,
I wish not to be selected as a concubine.
(Zhen Huan)
This is a wish fulfilling temple.
My Lady, your wish will come true.
My Lady, every other girl is wishing to be
selected while you want the opposite.
(left: Vermilion)
(right: Jade)
The Buddha will always remember you.
Shh! A wish will not come true if you tell it.
(Wen Shichu)
[an imperial doctor]
Look! It's Dr. Wen!
Is he here to make a wish?
Dr. Wen has been strange lately.
Imperial doctors cannot pay home visits without the Emperor's permission.
But he's been a frequenter of our residence.
Stop it!
I'll ask Dr. Wen for a prescription to cure gossiping.
Hello, Shichu!
Huan'er.
[Huan->Huan'er is a nickname like Max -> Maxie].
I was paying a routine visit to your parents,
and your mother told me that you came to the temple.
I was just taking a walk.
Huan'er, you don't have to hide from me.
I know you have been worried about the Final Selection lately.
I did my best, and Buddha will do the rest.
Huan'er, this heirloom jade teapot is a symbol of pure love.
My father would like me to give it to my future ...
I have always wanted to marry you.
And you don't have to attend the Selection if you're married.
The prior emperors demanded that qualified girls for
the Selection should not be arranged into marriage.
Thank you for trying to help, but the
jade teapot is too valuable for me.
Sorry, I cannot accept it.
Huan'er, I know I am just an undistinguished doctor.
But I promise to cherish and protect you all my life.
I will put you before anything else.
I am satisfied just to see you whenever I pay visits to your parents.
But you were unexpectedly selected,
and I know you are unwilling to...
Shichu, I'm sorry that I do not feel the same about you.
I always see you as my elder brother.
And you treated me like your own sister.
I believe you will marry the girl you really love.
I'm sorry for the sudden proposal.
But I really wanted to spare you from the Selection.
Not only for my feelings about you,
but also for my gratitude to your father,
who saved my father's life.
(whisper: why is it taking so long?)
Our families have long been friends.
It was our pleasure to help. Think nothing of it.
My father was incriminated because of the rivalries in the harem.
Even an imperial doctor can fall victim to the
competitive harem, let alone a concubine inside it.
I understand your concern.
But even if I avoid the Selection,
my younger sister will have to go the next time.
My parents only have two daughters,
and I don't want to put my sister through the Selection.
(whisper) She's gorgeous!
(Shen Meizhuang)
Let me look at you, Meizhuang.
Walk around.
Miss Shen walks with grace.
His Majesty will like her slender waist.
Now, talk.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesties.
My name is Shen Meizhuang.
Good. Very well mannered.
What if His Majesty asks about your education?
I studied Poetry, Confucianism, and History.
Wrong.
His Majesty is selecting concubines to have children with.
Not scholars.
"The lack of talent is the virtue in a woman."
Thanks, I understand.
(the hall for the Final Selection)
Greetings, Mr. Huang.
Come together you all.
(Huang Guiquan)
Consort Fleur sent me to inspect your work
as the Final Selection will be held here in ten days.
The hall must be presented in pristine condition.
Otherwise, you would offend Her Highness
at the expense of your lives.
Yes, Mr. Huang.
Now get back to work!
Please eat, Your Majesty.
Just one more moment.
It's been over ten days since His Majesty came for dinner.
Consort Fleur has sent someone to wait for His Majesty.
He is likely to have dinner with her tonight.
Your Majesty should eat if you are hungry.
It's almost the day for the Final Selection.
I am certain His Majesty will come today.
Your Majesty, Nian Gengyao is a successful general,
but a success is easier made than kept.
Do you view his new-found fame with caution?
Only Your Majesty can be the judge.
I hope I am overthinking.
I shall take my leave.
Your Majesty, the tea is cold.
I will change it for you.
It's all right.
Zhou Ninghai from Consort Fleur's palace
is waiting for Your Majesty outside.
Her Highness wishes to have dinner with you.
I desire not to go.
Er...
Your Majesty prefers to ...
I will eat with the Empress.
His Majesty is leaving for Palace of Great Benevolence.
Your Highness, the food is cold.
Should I reheat it now?
(Palace of Earthly Honor)
Not until His Majesty arrives.
(Zhou Ninghai)
[staggering]
Your Highness, His Majesty is going to eat at Palace of Great Benevolence.
All right then.
Please don't be upset, Your Highness.
About what?
She's the Empress after all.
She deserves a meal with His Majesty.
I just thought that they only eat together on the 15th of each month.
This is delicious!
Thanks, I made it myself.
(slight sigh) You are the Empress,
you should let the servants cook.
I am your empress and your wife.
It is a pleasure to cook for you.
It is a fusion of flavors.
Autumn.
Your Majesty, our ancestors believed
that a third helping is excess eating.
If you are going to have the third serving,
I'm afraid the soup will not be made again in a while.
Thank you for your reminder.
Healthy eating requires balance and self-restraint.
That not only holds true for food, but also for people.
Is that what you wish to tell me?
Your Majesty reads my mind.
Your Majesty likes eggplant. Have some more.
[Again, implications of his consorts]
"Eat in silence, sleep in quietness."
[Using ancestors' words against her]
Would Your Majesty like some tea?
No, thank you. I will go check out Consort Fleur.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Here.
You shouldn't be waiting outside.
It's cold out here.
I couldn't help.
I don't remember seeing you before.
Your Majesty, the Empress sent me to work here.
Hmm, she's pretty.
She belongs here.
How old are you?
I'm seventeen.
Seventeen.
A young girl indeed.
I remember you were her age when you married me.
Your Majesty surely has a good memory.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Please line up according to your Banners.
Two in a row.
Please remember that
when you meet His Majesty and Her Majesty the Empress Dowager,
try to relax and show good manners.
[the author is the women in jade blue]
Those who are not selected will be bestowed a flower to return home.
If you are selected, you might be arranged to marry a prince.
The luckiest ones will be the new concubines of His Majesty.
New concubines will officially move into
the palace after their ranks are assigned.
I wish everyone the best of luck.
[Good luck Meizhuang!]
Hold on.
Let's go.
What happened, Miss?
You arrived behind schedule.
Greetings, Madam.
The gates are closing soon.
Your year-long effort would have been wasted were you late.
(An Lingrong)
Sorry, I was coming from afar and the horse was slow.
My apologies for the delay.
Never mind, go in quickly.
Thank you so much, Madam.
I will always remember your kindness!
You are so sweet.
Go quickly, follow them.
Thank you.
Good luck!
[Why am I so pretty? I don't wanna be here.]
—Meizhuang!
—Huan'er!
I've always wanted to congratulate you on passing the previous rounds.
I wish I had not.
How was your trip to Beijing?
It was all right. I am well-rested after a few days.
I miss the time we were neighbors when
you were living with your grandparents.
You were just a wall away and we could see each other all the time.
I always remember the good times we had growing up together.
Are you keeping a low profile today?
But how could anyone not notice your gorgeous face?
No, you are the belle of the ball.
You dressed up so nicely. How can
His Majesty take his eyes off you?
Everyone here is very competitive.
We must be careful about what we say.
Xia Ruhua, daughter of the Mayor of Jiaxing City, is not selected.
Bestow the flower.
Fu Hua, daughter of the Deputy Minister
of the Petition Department, is not selected.
Bestow the flower.
Cao Xiangyu, sister of the
Deputy Minister of Personnel, is not selected.
Bestow the flower.
Lin Qingyun, daughter of the Assistant General
of the Infantry, is not selected.
Bestow the flower.
What is the matter with you?
How dare you pour the tea on my dress!
How impetuously loud in the imperial palace!
I'm so sorry.
Answer me! What family are you from?
My... my name is An Lingrong.
My father... is...
Are you too embarrassed to even say his position?
He is the Assistant Magistrate of Songyang Village.
(sneer)
An unknown family from a nameless place
can raise no daughter of style and grace.
Did you know this is Miss Xia,
daughter of Brigadier Xia?
I was nervously walking in the palace,
not paying enough attention.
I do beg your pardon for my inadvertence.
His Majesty will not select you regardless.
What is there to be nervous about?
It is your undeserved privilege to meet His Majesty in the palace.
What else can you reasonably expect?
If you are upset about your dress, I will make a compensation.
(sneer) With what?
Let's look at your own dress.
It's new, but loosely woven.
And the design has been out of style for 2 years.
My dress was made of Suzhou embroidery.
[the best silk and weaving technique]
Are you compensating me with your rusted silver hairpins?
Or your tacky gold-plated bracelets?
It is entirely my fault. How can I make it up to you?
I can forgive you if you kneel down and bow to me.
Leave them be. You should not add fuel to the fire.
Miss Xia is much more likely to be selected.
Go kneel!
It's not worthwhile being angry over a dress.
Who are you?
I am Zhen Huan, daughter of the Deputy Minister of Judicial Review.
A deputy minister? Not a high position.
It's not about the position. It's about being reasonable.
Do you think you can tell me what to do
because you have a pretty face that can get you selected?
I do not. I am simply thinking for you.
We do not want to disturb His Majesty with the accident over your dress.
We would not be able to justify ourselves
should His Majesty inquire about the disturbance.
Besides, your reputation would be tarnished by this.
Please think twice before you punish Lingrong.
I will remember you.
Everyone will remember you for your beauty.
Are you all right?
Thank you so much for your help.
I will never forget your benevolence.
Think nothing of it.
Miss Xia is spiteful in nature.
Do you worry about that?
No, I do not. Let her worry about it.
It was very reckless of you to speak out.
This is...
This is Meizhuang.
Nice to meet you, Meizhuang.
My pleasure.
A girl is judged by the way she dresses.
Not everyone is able to appreciate the elegant simplicity of your dress.
I'd like you to have the earrings as a gift.
No, I should not accept it.
I wish you the best of luck.
Thank you for your generosity.
But I may be too humble to repay it.
Where you come from does not determine what you can become.
(His Majesty summons An Lingrong and five other girls)
Good luck.
An Lingrong, 16, the daughter of the
Assistant Magistrate of Songyang Village.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesties.
Bestow the flower.
I thank Your Majesties and bid Your Majesties farewell.
I wish Your Majesty eternal peace and happiness.
Everyone else was displeased with the offer of a flower.
But you expressed your gratitude.
I feel extremely blessed to have a chance
to greet Your Majesties in the palace.
I like the crabapple flower on your hair.
Imperial Mother, let's not give her
the flower since she already has one.
An Lingrong is selected. Bestow the sachet.
(quiet sob) Dad and mom, I was selected!
I was selected!
I did not let you down! I made it!
They are just average.
Nobody is perfect.
Your priority is children, not perfection.
That one.
Xia Dongchun, 18, daughter of Brigadier Summer.
She has an interesting name. She's selected.
[xia = summer, dong = winter, chun = spring]
(gasp)
I thank Your Majesty.
Bestow the sachet.
Shen Meizhuang, 17, daughter of the Governor of Jizhou Province.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesties.
My name is Meizhuang Shen.
Are you educated?
I studied Rules For Women and Advice For Women.
They are good books for women.
Did you have a chance to study Confucianism?
Regretfully, I have not. [lying]
Girls are expected to spend most of their time on needlework.
I'm impressed that you are literate.
I thank Your Majesties.
You are selected.
Bestow the sachet.
Zhen Huan, 17, daughter of
the Deputy Minister of Judicial Review.
May peace and grace be with Your Majesties.
My name is Zhen Huan.
Zhen Huan ... What is the character for Huan?
As in “The slender beauties in King Chu's palace”.
It was a poem by Cai Shen.
Yes.
You are educated, I appreciate that.
I wonder if you are a slender beauty.
Raise your head.
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: liberapay.com/ZHZSubbers
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
But before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me was the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.